<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-18T07:22:59+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Navaneeth&apos;s Home on the Internet. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The vulnerability in Log4j (simply) explained</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/log4j/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The vulnerability in Log4j (simply) explained"/><published>2021-12-17T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-17T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/log4j</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/log4j/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/log4j_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/log4j_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/log4j_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/log4j_1.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Recently, a critical vulnerability in the popular software library Log4j was disclosed, which caused the internet to catch fire. And rightly so, because Log4j is used almost everywhere. There are numerous news articles, blogs, videos and lots of other content being published every day about Log4j ever since the vulnerability (coined Log4shell) came out, and it can get a bit overwhelming to try to keep up with everything for someone who wants to know what all the fuss is about. This blog is an attempt to provide a simplified view of what Log4j is, the implications of the vulnerability and what you can do to stay protected.</p> <p>In a nutshell, Log4j is a piece of software used for logging (surprise!) activities by users of an application as well as general application behaviour. Almost all applications perform some form of logging, as logs can be very useful to find unusual behaviour and troubleshoot issues, and many of them use Log4j for this purpose. In its essence, it is an open-source software library, which means developers can use it for free instead of building a logging mechanism from scratch. So when there’s a vulnerability in such a widely used piece of software, things tend to get a bit messy. The vulnerability was found in a component known as JNDI (Java Naming and Directory Interface) within Log4j.</p> <p>The vulnerability is something called remote code execution, commonly known as RCE. It means that malicious actors can execute commands of their choice on the vulnerable application. You may be realising the implications of this. Imagine how many systems can be compromised if you were allowed to execute anything you want on them. To make things worse, this vulnerability can be exploited easily compared to other RCEs. In some cases, it may be as simple as typing something into a chatbox.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/log4j_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/log4j_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/log4j_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/log4j_2.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Log4j is distributed and maintained for free by the Apache Software Foundation, and they were working frantically to come up with a patched version. Version 2.16.0 has been released now, which fixes the vulnerability. However, there is still news going around that the issue may not be fully fixed yet, and the impact of this vulnerability may be felt for a very long time in the future.</p> <p>To stay protected as an individual, the best thing you can do is to update all your software and firmware to the latest version and make sure to keep everything updated in the future as well. All software vendors are releasing patches as you are reading this to fix the issue. You can find a list of software that is vulnerable/not vulnerable <a href="https://github.com/NCSC-NL/log4shell/blob/main/software/README.md">here</a>. To help organizations stay protected, the National Cybersecurity Centre (NCSC) in the UK has published an article on what organizations can do in light of the vulnerability, which can be found <a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/news/apache-log4j-vulnerability">here</a>.</p> <p>I realise there are not many technical details in this blog. I have tried to keep it simple, and there are numerous excellent resources already out there about the Log4j vulnerability which I can’t even hope to match in quality and detail. Some of my favourites are linked below.</p> <p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/johnhammond010/">John Hammond</a>’s video on Log4j where he exploits a vulnerable Minecraft Server: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7qoPDq41xhQ&amp;t=875s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7qoPDq41xhQ&amp;t=875s</a></p> <p>A tweet by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/naomi-buckwalter/">Naomi Buckwalter</a> about the implications of this vulnerability: <a href="https://twitter.com/ineedmorecyber/status/1470224616375439369">https://twitter.com/ineedmorecyber/status/1470224616375439369</a></p> <p>The TryHackMe room Solar, which allows you to practice exploiting the vulnerability: <a href="https://tryhackme.com/room/solar">https://tryhackme.com/room/solar</a></p> <p>You may also want to check out the CVE on the National Vulnerability Database of NIST: <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2021-44228">https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2021-44228</a></p> <hr/> <p>The entire infosec community has been working very hard to stay on top of the issue, find as many vulnerable applications as possible, patch vulnerable software, and raise awareness about the issue. A huge shoutout to everyone for everything they are doing!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="cyber"/><category term="vulnerability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A simple explanation about the vulnerability in Log4j.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building an Information Risk Management Framework</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/irmf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building an Information Risk Management Framework"/><published>2021-12-09T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-09T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/irmf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/irmf/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/irmf_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/irmf_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/irmf_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/irmf_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>While pursuing a career in information security, we may be required to build something known as an information risk management framework (IRMF) somewhere down the line. It is a document that helps record and manage risks faced by an organization, thereby helping them get a better understanding of measures to be taken to minimize risk while working towards their business goals.</p> <p>During the second semester of my Master of Cybersecurity degree at The University of Adelaide, I enrolled in a course called Information Risks, Threats and Controls, where we were split into groups of seven to build an IRMF for real clients in Adelaide. It was a challenging yet wonderful experience, where I learned a lot about how organizations can manage and minimize the risks they face.</p> <p>We followed a nine-step risk assessment management (RAM) process to build the IRMF, which included the following steps:</p> <p><strong>RAM 1 — Establish context:</strong> Perhaps the most important step to take while building an IRMF is to establish context, as all other steps are influenced by the organizational context. We needed to gather as much information as possible about our client from the internet, people working in the organization, and interviews conducted with the director of the organization. Using this information, we prioritized our organization’s business goals and worked on building the IRMF accordingly.</p> <p><strong>RAM 2 — Identify risks:</strong> The next step was to identify the organization’s risks, which started with listing down its information assets. Then, potential threats to these assets and vulnerabilities present in the organization were identified, and risks were determined from this information.</p> <p><strong>RAM 3 — Map risks:</strong> We collected templates and tools commonly used in risk analysis, such as a risk matrix, to help analyse and communicate risks better. The information we gathered was mapped onto these templates.</p> <p><strong>RAM 4 — Analyse risks:</strong> Once we had the risks mapped out, we started the process of analysing the risks. We tried to find out how they could be related to each other so that reducing some risks could reduce others too.</p> <blockquote> <p>If you don’t invest in risk management, it doesn’t matter what business you’re in, it’s a risky business.</p> <p>– Gary Cohn</p> </blockquote> <p><strong>RAM 5 — Evaluate risks:</strong> The identified risks were evaluated to differentiate the extremely severe ones with a high impact on the organization from the low severity ones.</p> <p><strong>RAM 6 — Treat &amp; Control risks:</strong> Procedures that could be taken to treat the risks, and prevent further risks in the organization were considered and documented, along with our recommendations to the organization based on their context.</p> <p><strong>RAM 7 — Communicate &amp; Consult about risks:</strong> All the identified risks and measures to treat and control them were documented in a draft IRMF and sent to the organization for review so that the necessary changes could be made according to their take on our work.</p> <p><strong>RAM 8 — Monitor &amp; Review risks:</strong> The risks and mitigation techniques detailed in the draft were reviewed based on the organization’s suggestions. No matter how hard we tried to reflect the real scenario of the organization in our work, there were bound to be minor differences between what we stated and what they experienced, which were rectified during this review so that everyone was on the same page.</p> <p><strong>RAM 9 — Document risks &amp; Risk management strategies:</strong> All suggested changes were made and the final version of the IRMF was delivered to the organization, along with a brief report that stated how the IRMF was to be used and updated in the future.</p> <p>As evident, it was quite an elaborate process, which we worked on for 12 weeks. In the end, both our client and our lecturer were happy with our work, and hopefully, the organization could use it to improve their risk posture and manage their risks better.</p> <hr/> <p>I wrote this blog so that anyone who wanted to build an IRMF could refer to these steps and it would hopefully act as a solid base to build upon. Our final IRMF is linked <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1NBQ-mu7wGTleEdhYezf-KdQ19PqObTYW/view?usp=sharing">here</a> if anyone wants to check it out. The name of the organization and all sensitive details have been redacted.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="cyber"/><category term="infosec"/><category term="risk-management"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A brief description of the methodology used to build an IRMF.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My experience with the eJPT</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/ejpt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My experience with the eJPT"/><published>2021-06-27T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-27T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/ejpt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/ejpt/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ejpt_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ejpt_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ejpt_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ejpt_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I started my journey into cybersecurity only after I graduated with a bachelor’s degree in Computer Science and Engineering. Strange, I know. I tried various niches of computer science, from website and application development to machine learning and computer vision, during my four years in university. But, a six-month internship soon after made me realise that I want to be in the security domain.</p> <p>I dabbled in penetration testing by participating in capture-the-flag challenges during live events and on websites like HackTheBox and TryHackMe. Like everyone else interested in offensive security, I want to eventually get my OSCP, but before that, I wanted something a bit more light-hearted to put my skills to the test. That’s when I came across this wonderful certificate called the eJPT.</p> <p>Now, don’t get me wrong. The eJPT is not a piece of cake. While hunting for information about this examination through the dense forests of Reddit and Twitter, I found instances of people passing off the eJPT as being “too easy”. If you are a cybersecurity professional working with complex networks and testing heavy web applications, that may be the case. But, for most of us looking for a way to test our basic penetration testing skills, this certificate is the perfect challenge.</p> <p>This was my first penetration testing examination. I started preparing for it in January 2021, but I had to pause for a few months after February as I started my master’s degree in cybersecurity. Keeping up with university work while preparing for the exam was a bit too hectic for me, so I decided I would finish my preparation during the semester break. On June 14, I resumed preparing for the exam, before clearing it on June 26 2021 in four hours.</p> <p>Enough about me. You are probably reading this for tips on how to pass, right? Here are a few from my experience.</p> <ul> <li>Everything you need to pass the exam is in the course material by INE, accessible for free with their starter pass. Yes, the lab time is more than sufficient. No, you don’t need to get a paid pass for the material.</li> <li>You may have read other blogs or reviews before this one, and you may have heard that the routing step is difficult and that you need to practice pivoting with external resources, or read highly technical blogs about how to pivot. That is not necessary at all to pass, and you can quote me on this. What they mean when they talk about “pivoting” in the exam is to find and access other networks from the network you are dropped into. As long as you cover the networking section of the course properly and you have completed the “Find the secret server” lab available in the same section, you’ll be fine.</li> <li>Although the programming section (Module 2 of the course) is useful, it is not necessary for the exam.</li> <li>The three black boxes you receive as a part of the material are tougher than the exam itself, so if you have a hard time with them, don’t worry about it.</li> <li>You have three days to complete the examination which consists of 20 multiple-choice questions. So relax, take your time and don’t be in a rush to submit. I know it may be overwhelming, but there’s no reason to feel so.</li> <li>You will have to create your username and password for the .ovpn file to connect to the exam environment, so you don’t have to spend time searching for credentials. You will receive instructions on how to do this after you get your voucher.</li> <li>Make sure you download the .rar file they give you when you start your exam and read the letter of engagement properly.</li> <li>Do your basic scan (enumerating ports and services) on every machine at the beginning itself. Don’t wait to finish up with a machine before starting your scan for the next one. Crucial information in other machines may be required to answer questions about a particular machine.</li> <li>The exam questions are in a jumbled order. They may not be in the same order as your findings, so read all the questions before you start answering them.</li> <li>Review all your answers before you submit them. I know this probably goes without saying, but I wanted to put it out there.</li> </ul> <p>You can also check <a href="https://github.com/navisk13/ejpt-resources">this</a> compilation of a few resources I made during my preparation for the exam.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ejpt_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ejpt_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ejpt_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ejpt_2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My eJPT certificate. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="cyber"/><category term="certification"/><category term="pentesting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I tackled the eJPT, and a few tips.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A beginner’s guide to the Dark Web</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/darkweb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A beginner’s guide to the Dark Web"/><published>2021-01-29T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/darkweb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/darkweb/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/darkweb_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/darkweb_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/darkweb_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/darkweb_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The dark web is a part of the internet that is not indexed by search engines. The terms deep web and dark web are often used interchangeably, but they have their differences. The deep web is content on the internet that requires some authentication to access and is protected from web crawlers. This includes data like bank account details, social media accounts and email services. 90–95% of the internet falls under the deep web category, and the remaining 5% of the internet is the surface web, accessible to anyone. The dark web is a subset of the deep web.</p> <p>The dark web can’t be accessed using a typical browser. Since it emphasizes privacy and anonymity, a specific browser called Tor is required to access the dark web. Once you’re inside, it’s messy and chaotic, not to mention extremely slow. You could end up in the wrong place while navigating through it, even if you never intended to. Websites on the dark web are pretty much like any other website, except they end in .onion, as opposed to .com or .org. Specific search engines like DuckDuckGo or Grams are required to index these sites.</p> <p>Privacy is enforced by routing your web request through a series of proxy servers across the globe, thereby making it impossible to trace the origin of your request back to you. Due to the increased levels of anonymity, the dark web is a hotbed of criminal activity. Everything from guns, drugs, hitmen and stolen credentials to malicious software and extremely offensive content is available. You can even hire a hacker if you wanted. But be warned that this same anonymity paves the way for a large number of scammers. Since you don’t know who’s on the other side, you can’t trust anybody. Even popular commerce sites on the dark web have absconded with their users’ money.</p> <blockquote> <p>Sometimes, we need to see the dark side to appreciate the light.</p> </blockquote> <p>Transactions are carried out on the dark web using cryptocurrencies like bitcoin, allowing users to transfer funds securely without knowing each other’s identity. Even though commerce sites on the dark web look legitimate, this is far from the truth. You can’t rely on the quality of what you’re buying, and product ratings are heavily manipulated. Even if you do complete a successful transaction, it’s doubtful if your product will ever arrive.</p> <p>Not everything on the dark web is illegal, though. Resources like hard-to-find books, political discussions, and even a dark web version of Facebook is available. You can browse websites on the surface using the Tor network as well. It is perfectly legal to access the dark web and is particularly useful for people who value their privacy. After all, the Tor network began as an anonymous communication channel. Even legitimate organizations like law enforcement use the dark web to keep an eye out for stolen data and security breaches.</p> <p>If you find your information published on the dark web, there’s nothing much you can do. Accept the fact that you have been compromised, and change any exposed credentials. If you’re curious, the dark web is worth a visit, provided you can tolerate the unreliability and extremely slow speeds. Just make sure you don’t dive into anything illegal.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="cyber"/><category term="awareness"/><category term="darkweb"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the dark side of the internet beyond cute cat videos.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All about torrents</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/torrents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All about torrents"/><published>2021-01-28T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/torrents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/torrents/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/torrents_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/torrents_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/torrents_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/torrents_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Torrents are a peer-to-peer (P2P) method of file sharing. Instead of using a centralized server, torrents allow you to download files from other computers. The same file can be downloaded from multiple systems at once, facilitated by the BitTorrent network. To download and upload files, you need to connect to the network using a torrent client available on the internet, like Vuze or uTorrent.</p> <p>On the BitTorrent network, a peer is someone who is uploading or downloading a file. A group of peers are known as a swarm. There are two kinds of peers; seeders and leechers. Seeders are peers who have downloaded the file fully on their system and have made it available for other peers to download. Leechers are peers who download what they want without hosting it for others. When the number of seeders is greater than the number of leechers, your download will be faster. It is also considered safer to download files with a high number of seeders.</p> <p>One concern users have about torrents is regarding their legality. The act of torrenting is legal, but the content hosted by peers may not be so. Downloading copyrighted material is illegal, and a third of all content downloaded using torrents are found to be copyrighted. Depending on your country, this could lead to severe consequences. For example, in Japan, owning illegal copyrighted material could fetch you up to ten years in prison. In India, there haven’t been any severe consequences on people downloading copyrighted content from torrents. That being said, I do not endorse downloading or owning illegal copyrighted material in any manner.</p> <blockquote> <p>There are two sides to every coin.</p> </blockquote> <p>Another concern about torrents is regarding safety and privacy. Since there are many illegal files hosted on the BitTorrent network, several malicious files come along with it. Usually, malware is hidden along with the actual file you requested, but there have been instances where malware is disguised as a legitimate file itself. Ultimately, it’s a gamble. If you want to use torrents, be prepared for the risk which comes with them. Like I mentioned before, files with a high number of seeders are less likely to be infected, so you can use this trick to be on the safe side.</p> <p>It is also advisable to use a VPN to mask your IP address from your ISP while downloading torrent files, thereby giving you an extra layer of security. Without a VPN, your ISP can monitor your activity on the BitTorrent network, and they may share this information with third parties like law enforcement authorities or the owners of the file.</p> <p>A large amount of copyright material is what makes torrents so popular. Torrents can’t be considered entirely safe, but using antivirus software and a VPN can dampen the risk. Now that you know how it works, you can make a better-informed decision about venturing into this world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="security"/><category term="awareness"/><category term="torrents"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read this before you download (il)legal content using torrents!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Securing your home wireless network</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/securewifi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Securing your home wireless network"/><published>2021-01-27T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-27T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/securewifi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/securewifi/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/securewifi_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/securewifi_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/securewifi_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/securewifi_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The internet is an essential commodity for most people in the 21st century, and the number of home networks is rising, especially with many jobs going remote due to the pandemic.</p> <p>Some people may opt for a wired connection since they have to connect only one device (a single PC or laptop) to the internet, but most people prefer a wireless network so that every member of the family can reap the benefits of the internet on multiple devices at home.</p> <p>The simplest way to set up a wireless network is to get a wireless router and plug it in. Simple, yes, but it is also the least secure way to access the internet.</p> <p>A wireless router comes with its own set of security risks which may leave your network potentially vulnerable, leading to higher internet bills, sensitive information disclosure, unauthorized access to your devices, and even termination of your internet connection due to illegal activity.</p> <p>Your router will come with a pamphlet, containing the default password for devices to connect to the network, along with the IP address (usually 192.168.1.1) and the default credentials to access the admin panel.</p> <p>The first thing you need to do soon after you’ve connected your router is to log in to the admin panel using the IP address from any of your devices and change the name of the router, also known as the SSID. This is the name anyone who attempts to connect to your network will see.</p> <p>Router names are set to the manufacturing company’s name by default, and sharing this information is not a good security practice. Avoid renaming it to anything that can be traced back to you (like “John’s WiFi”), but everything else is fair game.</p> <p>Make sure you change the password to your network too. Most routers require a password with a minimum length of eight characters. Follow best password practices, and choose a secure password that can’t be guessed easily. You’d be surprised at the number of routers with the password set to “12345678”.</p> <p>It is also mandatory to change the default credentials to the admin panel. All routers made by the same company will likely have the same credentials for the admin panel, so if anyone figures out the company’s name, they can potentially access your admin panel and gain full control over your network.</p> <blockquote> <p>Securing everything but your admin panel is like bolting all your windows and leaving the front door open.</p> </blockquote> <p>Okay, you’ve got the bare minimum covered. But, to ensure maximum security, there are a few other precautions you can take. Ensure that all your network traffic is encrypted.</p> <p>Your router will come with the option to choose the level of encryption you require. Make sure that you set it to WPA2, which is the industry standard right now. Encrypting your traffic is necessary to prevent anyone from capturing data packets from your network and getting access to sensitive information like passwords.</p> <p>Another precaution you can take is to turn off the wireless router when you’re not at home, or when not in use. Not only will it close any windows of opportunity for malicious hackers to gain access to your network, but it will also help reduce your internet and electricity bills.</p> <p>Most routers allow you to connect by pressing a button on the back of the router or using a pin instead of a standard password. It is also a good idea to disable these “quick connect” features on your device.</p> <p>Finally, make sure that the firmware on all your devices, not just the router, is up to date. Sometimes, all that a hacker needs is one flaw on any one of your devices to compromise your entire network. Keeping everything up to date is considered one of the most important security practices to follow. Good luck, and stay safe!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="security"/><category term="awareness"/><category term="privacy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Follow these best practices at home to ensure your network is safe.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing the right VPN</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/vpn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing the right VPN"/><published>2021-01-26T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/vpn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/vpn/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/vpn_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/vpn_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/vpn_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/vpn_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>A VPN (Virtual Private Network) gives you privacy and anonymity while surfing the web by encrypting your data and routing your web requests through a server anywhere around the globe. This helps by hiding your data packets and your IP address from your internet service provider, organization, and anyone else you share your network with. VPNs are especially useful when you’re using insecure public WiFi on the go. Think about all the times you’ve used a public network to pay bills or check your email.</p> <p>VPNs are necessary for anyone concerned about their online privacy, but very few people take their security seriously and use them. The most popular excuse people have for not using a VPN is the cost associated with it, but that’s a small price to pay compared to how valuable your information is on the black market. While using a VPN, even search engines can’t track your searches back to you, since they will be associated with an IP address that’s not yours. This will help protect you from annoying targeted advertisements.</p> <p>VPNs work by creating an encrypted data tunnel between your network and a server anywhere around the globe, making it seem like you’re in another place. Not only does this guarantee your privacy, but it can also help you access certain services that are only available in particular regions. A VPN protects your devices from prying eyes, especially on a public network, by hiding your data from cybercriminals on the same network.</p> <p>While choosing a VPN among the plethora of options available, it is necessary to ensure that your VPN has an active no-log policy, which means they can’t track your internet activity. If they can, then it beats the whole purpose.</p> <p>Most free VPNs log your browsing history, and they probably sell your data to third parties. Free VPNs also have annoying pop-up ads and a limited number of servers, leading to overcrowding and slower internet speeds. To avoid falling into this trap, use a paid VPN. They don’t cost much, and it’s a small price to pay for your privacy. Some paid VPNs have free versions as well, with a limit on how much data you can use.</p> <blockquote> <p>If you’re not paying for the product, you are the product.</p> </blockquote> <p>Ensure that the VPN of your choice uses a secure encryption protocol like OpenVPN, which also happens to be open source. Also, find out where their servers are located, in case you want to access content available only at particular locations. Make sure you go through any other restrictions they may have, like data limits and the number of devices you can use it on, to avoid hassles in the future. It is also a good idea to go for a VPN with a kill switch. In case your VPN connection is interrupted, a kill switch can help by severing your connection to the internet so that your device doesn’t automatically connect to insecure networks.</p> <p>Since there are many factors to consider, make sure you do your homework while choosing your VPN and see what fits you best. Do not worry about the cost; rest assured that a good VPN will provide more privacy and security than any WiFi network can.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="security"/><category term="awareness"/><category term="privacy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Find out everything you need to look for while choosing a VPN for your device.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it safe to use a password manager?</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/pwman/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it safe to use a password manager?"/><published>2021-01-25T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/pwman</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/pwman/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pwman_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pwman_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pwman_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/pwman_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Passwords are the key to unlocking pretty much anything on the internet today. It can’t be emphasized enough how important they are to protect netizens around the globe. But, password security is rarely taken seriously. More often than not, people use the same password for every account. If one password is compromised, then everything else goes down with it. Some passwords aren’t even secure and can be guessed by knowing a few details about their owner.</p> <blockquote> <p>Anything that’s on your resume should not be used as a password.</p> </blockquote> <p>Choosing a unique password that can’t be traced back to you in any way and remembering where each password is used is not an easy thing to do. That’s why password managers like 1Password and LastPass have become so popular recently. They allow you to store all your passwords behind an encrypted vault. All you need to remember is one master password to access the vault. Even the people behind the password manager won’t have access to your passwords, as they use zero-knowledge architecture. This means that your passwords are encrypted before they leave your device, so they can’t be decrypted even when they end up on the company server.</p> <p>But, are password managers safe? Well, not entirely, but it is your best bet to stay secure. It is better than reusing passwords everywhere, and that’s precisely why you should use a password manager anyway. Security is a grey area; no product can be considered completely bug free and secure, but you can rest assured that bugs are patched as soon as they’re found.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pwman_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pwman_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pwman_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/pwman_2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The most valuable piece of information about your password manager is your master password. Make sure it is strong and unique. Write it down and keep it in a secure physical location, in case you forget it. It is impossible to become 100% secure, but it is certainly possible to not be low hanging fruit to hackers.</p> <p>Now, you may be wondering why you need a password manager at all when browsers like Chrome and Firefox (I don’t use other browsers, so I can’t speak for them) have integrated password managers. Well, for starters, browser-based password managers are dependent on your browser. If you store a password on Chrome, it won’t be available on Firefox, and vice versa. This could prove to be a hassle unless you save all your passwords on both browsers, which isn’t a good idea because now you have to protect two locations instead of just one. This brings me to my next point: your browser’s default password manager isn’t nearly as secure as its independent counterparts anyway.</p> <blockquote> <p>Passwords are like toothbrushes; change them often and do not share.</p> </blockquote> <p>On Linux, Chrome will let anyone view all the saved passwords on the browser without any authentication. On Windows, it is protected by your Windows password, which is more often than not insecure and used by multiple people. Anyone who uses your computer will be able to see all your passwords. Firefox, on the other hand, will give anyone access to your passwords regardless of the platform unless a master password is set. Since most people aren’t aware of the master password feature, that’s pretty insecure too.</p> <p>In some cases, physical access to the device isn’t necessary either. Anyone with remote access to your computer will be able to see all your passwords in plain sight. So yes, use a password manager, but don’t use the default one on your browser.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="security"/><category term="awareness"/><category term="passwords"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We rely on password managers to remember all our unique passwords for us. But how secure are they?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What does WhatsApp’s new privacy policy mean for its users?</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/whatsapp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What does WhatsApp’s new privacy policy mean for its users?"/><published>2021-01-17T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/whatsapp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2021/whatsapp/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/whatsapp_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/whatsapp_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/whatsapp_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/whatsapp_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>WhatsApp has updated its privacy policy in early 2021, and all of its 2 billion users must accept it if they want to continue using the popular messaging app. According to the notifications received by users (written in legal jargon not easily interpreted by the average user), WhatsApp reserves the right to share information it collects about you to other Facebook products, such as Instagram, regardless of whether you have an account on those platforms. This data includes your usage habits and your phone’s unique ID, among other metadata. Your conversations on WhatsApp are still safe, though.</p> <p>Users had the option of sharing their data with Facebook since 2016, but as of May 15th, it will be mandatory for all users. Initially, the policy was to be enforced on February 8th, but WhatsApp decided to postpone the date owing to the massive confusion and concerns among users. The policy also stated that Facebook would be giving companies the option to use Facebook servers for their business needs. This means that companies may choose to store backups of conversations you have with WhatsApp business accounts on Facebook servers.</p> <p>Even though businesses have the option of storing conversations on Facebook servers, Facebook will not have access to those files. What businesses do with the information shared during the conversation is entirely up to them. Any privacy concerns must be clarified with the business directly.</p> <blockquote> <p>Your privacy is a myth.</p> </blockquote> <p>There is a lot of confusion regarding this new policy. WhatsApp faced a lot of heat, and many users jumped ship to alternate apps like Signal and Telegram. Signal especially faced an unprecedented surge in the number of users, which led to a delay for users in receiving confirmation codes due to heavy server loads. However, users can rest assured that WhatsApp can’t read your conversations with your friends and family, as all chats are still end-to-end encrypted. Even if WhatsApp gets access to chat files, they won’t be able to decrypt it. It’ll just be a load of gibberish. This holds for both personal and business accounts.</p> <p>In conclusion, deciding to leave WhatsApp or to continue using the application is entirely up to the user. Most of the apps and services you use every day collect your metadata for various purposes. Since we rarely read their privacy policies while making an account, we agree to everything unknowingly. WhatsApp just had the decency to notify us about it specifically. There’s no need to panic over the new privacy policy. Your chats are safe, and a small amount of compromise in privacy is applicable for any service you use online, not just WhatsApp.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="security"/><category term="privacy"/><category term="whatsapp"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Everything you need to know about WhatsApp’s new privacy policy explained in a crisp and concise article.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All about OSINT</title><link href="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2020/osint/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All about OSINT"/><published>2020-10-19T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2020/osint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://navisk13.github.io/blog/2020/osint/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/osint_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/osint_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/osint_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/osint_1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>In the world of hacking, when you’ve chosen a target to attack, there’s a crucial step you must perform before moving in with all guns blazing — Information Gathering, or Reconnaissance. It is necessary to gather as much knowledge about your target as possible before you start your attack. For example, if you’re targeting a software company, knowledge of the number of employees, scale of the company and strength of their security team could prove to be useful to carry out a more focused attack, and OSINT is the primary step you can take to start collecting this information.</p> <p>Open Source Intelligence, also known as OSINT, is defined as the process of collecting information about your target from openly available sources. Some may think that OSINT is just a fancy word for “googling”, but there’s much more to OSINT than a simple Google search. You can get details about your target’s network, the IP addresses they’re using, and even their entire infrastructure when OSINT is done properly and extensively. Don’t limit yourself to Google while performing OSINT; check out anything and everything you can think of about your target. Don’t leave any stone unturned. You never know when something might be useful to you.</p> <p>OSINT can be carried out in two ways; either active or passive. Active OSINT is the information you gather when you have direct contact with your target. Considering the example of the software company, going on an office tour to check out their infrastructure, noticing any security measures implemented and meeting their employees can be classified as active OSINT. Passive OSINT, on the other hand, is when you gather information about your target with no direct contact. Collecting contact information like phone numbers and email addresses from their website, or triggering error messages in their products to check for data leaks can be classified as passive OSINT.</p> <p>The main objectives of OSINT are to know the security posture of your target, so that you get a fair understanding of how they’ll respond to an attack, to identify vulnerabilities in your target to get a pathway to compromise them and to draw a network map with all the information you’ve collected so that you get a broad idea of their infrastructure. If you’re lucky enough to get information such as IP addresses or network blocks, you can use this knowledge to carry out a more focused attack, saving you the time of trying to attack everything to see what clicks.</p> <blockquote> <p>Security is just an illusion and privacy is a myth.</p> </blockquote> <p>There are many tools available to help with OSINT. One of the most popular tools is archive.org, also known as the Wayback machine, which can be used to get older versions of websites to check for any revealed sensitive information patched recently. Another popular tool is Maltego, available for both Linux and Windows. It’s an advanced OSINT tool, with a wide array of features to collect various kinds of information. Netcraft is another popular website you can use to get a list of subdomains of a particular website.</p> <p>Now that you know how OSINT works, and how you can gather tons of information about your target from various sources, how do you stop someone from doing the same to you? The simplest way is to limit the information you reveal about yourself on the internet. This can apply to both individuals as well as organizations. In case you do need to store sensitive information somewhere online, make sure it’s encrypted and password protected. Use pseudonyms on public forums and chat rooms, so that nobody can trace the username back to you. Make sure security awareness camps are conducted in your organization periodically so that employees know how to identify and protect sensitive information.</p> <hr/> <p>For more details on OSINT, and a demo of some interesting OSINT tools, you can check out my session on OSINT presented at EvilWeek by EvilHoursX <a href="https://bit.ly/3o7ywZq">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="security"/><category term="social-engineering"/><category term="hacking"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Find out what OSINT really is, and how you can use it too.]]></summary></entry></feed>